[Music]
there's one thing every human on this
planet can agree with it's that farting
is hilarious let's try to get through
these next few minutes without laughing
and giggling too much so of all the
foods you eat carbohydrates proteins in
fact the vast majority of your gas
actually comes from the carbohydrates
it's not the protein or the eggs and
even though they smell like that that's
not usually the cause of why you're 40
so if we break down carbohydrates
there's three main types sugars starches
and fibers and I've explained these in
detail in other videos but here's what
typically happens here you have your
stomach that feeds into your small
intestines those feeding your large
intestines which are called your colon
and then it goes out to record okay well
what usually happens is you've got
enzymes that are in all three of those
areas and mostly in the small intestines
that are able to break down food if
things are digested there you have no
real issues and so most of your sugars
and starches are easily digested in the
small intestine it gets quickly in the
bloodstream and you're off easy peasy
however there are some types of sugars
that we don't have the enzymes and our
small intestine for it and so those
actually transfer all the way through to
the large intestine and they're not
haven't been digested or broken down yet
because they require a different enzyme
and so those have to be rapidly
fermented in the larger intestine
well actually the only way we do that is
since humans don't have those enzymes we
have to use in other species and those
are gut bacteria so the gut bacteria
have the enzymes necessary to break
these things down well as a byproduct of
those things when taba lysing the food
they kick out what are called short
chain fatty acids and as you guessed it
a little bit of gas so anytime we're
really talking about digestion happening
in the lower intestine versus a smaller
intestine that's typically where our gas
is coming from now those types of sugars
that require that are generally
categories categorized and called
FODMAPs
okay so in sugars or starches and a good
example is rice that that can be
digested in the small intestine are not
going to give you gas so if you just
look for this type of starches that are
more digested there you're gonna be fine
okay now
you're FODMAPs or whatever called
rapidly fermentable illegal dyin
monosaccharides as well as a thing
called polyols now polyols are what we'd
also the moment care about the most are
called sugar alcohols and those are
probably the ones that are responsible
for the protein more farts if you've
ever had that it's not the protein in
there and of the FODMAPs probably
raffinose is by far our biggest problem
area and that's because it's in high
concentrations in beans cabbage broccoli
asparagus etc okay so another part
starts as typically an offender of gas
are called
resistant starches and so these are
similar idea they're an actually rapidly
fermented in about five mats but they're
slowly fermented and a larger intestine
gonna cause you the same particular
problems and then fiber as well so any
other rapid or slow ferment that needs
to be rapidly are slowly fermented and
large intestines is gonna count for that
problem as well and then of fiber there
are there's a final category that are
but we often call NSPS or non starchy
polysaccharides that are just simply
never digested at all and those actually
make it to the entire part of the body
like cellulose pectin cetera and they're
never actually broken down so while
these foods are commonly resulting in
gas you don't necessarily want to get
rid of them as you can see here they
have a number of very important health
benefits like keeping your colon healthy
and keeping you cancer-free or reducing
your cancer risk they can help you
regulate blood cholesterol blood glucose
and a bunch of other things important to
your health and while eliminating them
may reduce your say gaseous emissions
they don't necessarily cause unless we
don't have any scientific evidence to
suggest they cause things like irritable
bowel syndrome Crohn's or our gut
inflammation so don't conflate those two
we see this misappropriated a lot on the
internet with gurus and things like that
they don't really understand this they
don't cause inflammation there's simply
a symptom or assignment so don't worry
about these things giving you that all
they're really common causes of GI
issues is you know it's too many
carbohydrates at once too much of an
increase in these fog
resistance arches fibers or NSPS so it's
not that they caused it but you just go
from too little to too many too quickly
so we're gonna slower you could have
some innate sensitivity or allergy just
something that you're eating like gluten
dairy something like that could have
some stomach issues or you could even
have what's called SIBO small intestinal
bacterial overgrowth so the bacteria is
supposed to be in your large intestine
gets in your small intestine and you can
see where that's particularly a problem
okay if you want to see me go into
detail of all these things more and how
those ones that are circled in red
actually cause an auto inflammatory or
autoimmune response rather you also want
to see more about these recommendations
so typically we're gonna say you have
about 14 to 16 grams of fiber total in
your diet per thousand calories you eat
so if you eat 2,000 double that 3,000
triple that more specifically the
different types of fiber soluble or
insoluble how to get these in different
foods as well as solutions for this
you're gonna have to watch the larger 55
minute video so one thing things you can
explore are our strategies involving
increasing your pre and probiotics with
a supplementation or food or just simply
taking digestive enzymes if we know
that's the issue when we can get some of
these digestive enzymes in or stomach or
potentially small intestines that may
help but as you'll see in the other
video there's a whole host of problems
with these strategies and so just to
tease that larger video one more time
this is a list of the 22 different
things that I cover in that video in
addition to this but you can read them
here so if you want to see these answers
and these topics watch another one if
not hopefully this explains you a little
bit about why you fart so much now maybe
if you want I'll make a separate video
explaining why they smell so bad
enjoy
[Music]